Okay, so as many of you may have already heard, the American Cancer Society fundraiser Relay for Life is this Friday night at Gordon Track.
The event increases awareness and raises money for cancer education, research, and treatment.
It's not too late to get involved either by registering online, donating to a participant, or showing up at the event to see what it's all about.
At the event, we will have Root Beer Beirut, a cappella and band performances, a missed relay pageant, and movies and games, and all the while, people will be walking laps around the track to remember those lost, celebrate survivors,
and hope for a future cure.
Look out for emails and check out our Facebook group for more information. I hope to see you all there. Thanks.
Hi, good morning.
We're going to pick up where we left off last time, but before we do,
a few of you came to me after class and asked about alternative forms of exercise. So the study that I gave, also what you read, the article by Callahan and others,
um is mostly about aerobic exercise and as i mentioned earlier this is about moderate intensity
workout which would mean if you want to work with pulse about 70 percent between 65 and 75 percent
of your maximum heart rate again you just google you know heart rate exercise and you'll
immediately get all the tables that you need um but that's one form of exercise some of you ask What about weight training? What about interval training?
So sprints and stops, sprints and stops, something that the crew team does often, athletes do often. What about this form?
The reason why I didn't bring it up explicitly in the lecture is because the jury is still out on the different forms of exercise.
But let me tell you what are some of the trends that we see in research.
right now it seems that if there is only one form of exercise that you do the best bang for the
buck best value for your time would be aerobic exercise three ideally four times 30 minutes
of aerobic exercise a week that's at minimum however however if you can also do weight training
and supplement the aerobic exercise, that's terrific, that's great.
Twice a week, three times a week of weight training is great, especially as you get older.
Weight training contributes more. But also at a very young age, weight training is good.
However, it is not a replacement for aerobic exercise. It hasn't shown to have the same psychological effects as aerobic exercise does.
the other form of exercise that has been studied and again these are all tentative results there have been pilot studies about it that the ends the sample sizes are not large enough yet to say
definitively just like we can say about aerobic exercise it has a similar effect to some of our most powerful psychiatric drugs that's definitive there are tons of studies on it ever since the
babiac 2000 as well as before but another form of exercise that has begun to be studied with
some very promising results is interval training interval training would be say running at between
90 and 95 percent of your maximum heart rate so if you're 20 and your maximum heart rate would be
would be 200 because it's 220 minus your age then it would be running at around 180 to 190
pulse rate, which is hard, which is tough, which you can't do for a very long time. But doing it for as little as 30 seconds up to a minute, and then resting, letting your
heart rate go back down to 60% of its maximum, say 120, and then doing another interval,
that has been shown with pilot studies only to have remarkable effects. In fact, often more powerful than aerobic exercise on its own.
and lasts for even longer the effect so again i did not introduce it officially as part of the class but since many of you asked i'm introducing it because what i want to introduce you are only
things that are with very robust results john rayte talks about this and i'll talk a little
bit about john rayte in a minute he's the harvard medical school psychiatrist who's probably the leading proponent and researcher in the area of exercise and mental health
And he himself, even though the results are still tentative, he introduces two interval trainings a week. So in addition to working out six days a week,
two of them include full-out sprinting, rest, full-out sprinting, rest.
And what they've shown is that with even less time than 30 minutes, you can get the same psychological effect and even better.
What I do twice a week, I introduce interval training.
So, for example, this morning when I was on my trampoline, I did it for 30 minutes, and out of the 30 minutes, there were four sprints, indeed.
You don't believe me that I do trampoline, do you? I'll videotape it.
Maybe not. Maybe not. Maybe not.
So, four sessions of sprints, and then I have my heart monitor on, going all the way, for me, it's about 165 heart rate, between 165 and 170.
and then resting, going back to about 110, which is more or less 60% of my maximum, and then doing it four times.
And for the rest of the 30 minutes, I just do moderate aerobic exercise. So I'll also introduce the interval training.
The weight training, I do less of because I get that from yoga,
a lot of the strengthening exercises. this. The most important thing though that I do want to say about interval training is
that especially for perfectionists, it's very easy to overtrain. You don't want to get to your maximum heart rate and keep it there for a long time, even if you can. More does
not necessarily mean better. Unless you're training for the Olympics, in which case
you do want to get to 100% of your maximum heart rate at times. For maximum health, you
want to get to 90% maximum 95% of your max heart rate which is why a heart rate monitor can help
so much because it can tell you when you're working too hard or when it's too easy bottom
line variety is good for exercise if you can introduce dancing that's a great exercise if you can introduce once in a while working out in the gym once in a while playing basketball
Rowing, the more variety, the better. But the foundation, at least three, ideally four times a week, 30 minutes of aerobic exercise.
So we stopped last time with overcoming barriers.
And some of the barriers are that it's difficult, there is some pain associated with it, even if you are at 70% of your heart rate. It's still uncomfortable.
And ways to deal with it is, at least until you get into it, because very often we enter the zone when we start to run and we don't feel the difficulty anymore.
But at least at the beginning, it's important to have social support, to divide and conquer, to build gradually, and to have distractions such as TV, your MP3 or whatever it is.
Another barrier, and this one is unfortunately very common here on campus, is that we just don't have time. You know, in high school, I give a lot of talks in high schools,
And one of the things that I see there is that students in many high schools actually have to be part of a team.
They have to, in addition to doing physical exercise, PE, they also have to be part of a team. So they get not enough, but more exercise.
Whereas one of the first things that go in college, especially or only for students who do not play on the team,
one of the first things that go is exercise i don't have time i have so many things i want to do it's a new world well it's also the first thing that goes during exam period because i'm so stressed
and i have so many things to do well it should be the last thing to go it should be the last thing
to go why because it is an investment you may be losing the 45 minutes you know that working out
for 30 minutes and showering after which i recommend you may lose that 45 minutes but you
will gain so much more it's such a good investment why because your memory actually gets better when
you exercise so you get more bang for the buck in terms of time you study your creativity level go up your concentration whether you have add or not especially if you have or you have a tendency
toward add or adhd but even for people without it concentration goes up significantly energy levels
go up significantly so it's a very good investment remember i told you the story when i stopped exercising at the end of the squash season and suddenly i said oh i have so much time and that
and i ended up getting so much less done a because i didn't have the rituals and b because i wasn't
as focused, I wasn't as creative, I wasn't as energized. It should be the last thing
to go, especially, especially during stressful periods such as exam period. One way to overcome
the time commitment, again, is not to rely on self-discipline. We've established that before we saw the research, we have a limited amount of self-discipline. Create rituals
where, say, three mornings during the week you'll do it, or if a good time for use, the
afternoon or evening but have a ritual around it another barrier to exercising regularly and this
is an interesting one and often overlooked but extremely powerful and that is the subconscious
barrier nathaniel brandon talks about this and i talk about it a little bit in in my book quoting
him he talks about self-esteem and part of self-esteem is the notion that we are worthy of
happiness the notion of being worthy of happiness and when you ask people are you worthy of happiness most people will say yes but if you ask the
subconscious very often for many people it's no whether it's because of the voices that we heard in the past teachers educators parents significant
adults society at large by comparing us to unrealistic models but very often we
we have this voice the subconscious level that we're not really worthy of happiness and that is
a barrier that stops us from becoming happier now one of the things that we know with exercise is
that it's one of the if not the most powerful drug for making us happier now i know that exercise
makes me happier it makes me feel good but if my subconscious thinks that i'm unworthy of these
feelings unworthy of being happy it may in fact stop me from exercising why because remember the mind doesn't like when there is an inconsistency between
what's inside and what's outside and if what's inside is saying shouldn't be
happy then I try to match it with what's inside and then I don't exercise
because if I do exercise then there will be a disconnect I will be happier
than i think i'm worthy of there's a lot of research on this one for example by psychologist
banano swan who talks about self-confirmation theory which is a very powerful force within us
there is a self-enhancement that we want to appear good in other people's eyes in our eyes
but there is a counter force which is self-confirmation where we want to confirm whatever we think about ourselves and if we think not worthy of happiness will
very often not do things that actually will make us happy we see it in other areas in relationships for example if I think I'm unworthy of a wonderful
partner of being happy in a relationship very often I will inadvertently subconscious work working here jeopardize the relationship and look for
things that are not working actively subconsciously look for ways of hurting
the relationship so we need to be aware of the subconscious level and it very much applies to whether or not we exercise so what do we do with this the
best thing to do is to just do it again ritualize it not analyze it too much just go ahead and exercise you know three four times a week is good for you
just do it and again it's the five-minute takeoff the subconscious mind will try and tell you don't do it you know you don't have time there are other
things you know you'll do it tomorrow next week you'll start the regime the subconscious mind is very smart in its attempt and will do anything that it can
almost to create this congruency and when you go out and exercise and you show yourself yes I am worthy of happiness very often the subconscious mind will
follow suit so just do it the second thing is recognize this is on the cognitive level recognize
how important physical exercise is remember what marty seligman said we mostly focus on neck up
and we do it as psychologists we do it as students in in an academic institution especially in a place like this so much is about thinking and cognition that's how you got here that's how you
you were successful, but it's no less important to think about neck down.
In fact, the mind alone can only take us so far when it comes to happiness, which is why I told you if I were a therapist,
a prerequisite for me to treat people would be to have them exercise regularly because I don't want to fight nature.
I want to work with nature and build on it.
Exercise in many ways is the unsung hero of psychological interventions.
It helps on so many levels. John Rattie mentioned him, Harvard Medical School professor, psychiatrist.
In a way, exercise can be thought of as a psychiatrist's dream treatment.
It works on anxiety, on panic disorder, and on stress in general,
which has a lot to do with depression.
And it generates the release of neurotransmitters, norepinephrine, serotonin, and dopamine that are very similar to our most important psychiatric medicines.
Having a bout of exercise is like taking a little bit of Prozac and a little bit of Ritalin right where it is supposed to go.
The exact right amount of it, the exact right location,
and without side effects or with side effects, positive side effects, physical as well as mental and emotional side effects.
What John Rattie is calling for in his wonderful, wonderful book, just came out recently in this January, what he calls for is an exercise revolution.
And he backs up this call with a lot of scientific evidence of why it is so important.
Let me share with you just one area that he talks about. He talks about all ages. He talks about kids, adults, as well as the elderly population.
and it has positive effects for every age, from 0 to 120.
Let me talk about a couple of studies and findings where exercise was implemented in schools.
So there are a few schools that introduced physical exercise as an integral part of its curriculum. For example, and this has been replicated in a few schools,
Every morning, 45 minutes of some form of exercise.
Usually running, sometimes rowing, cycling, climbing.
There's a school in New Jersey that actually put a climbing wall where students exercised.
But some form of aerobic exercise, sometimes intertwined with interval training, every morning before school, 45 minutes a day.
Some of the schools had it later during the day, most of them in the morning.
Here are some of the results from some of these schools that actually introduced it.
Obesity levels, not surprising, went down. For example, in Naperville in Illinois,
in the district there where physical exercise was introduced in school,
which is, by the way, interesting, because in most schools,
Just yesterday I gave a talk at Horace Mann, and the teachers told me that in many of the schools in New York, physical exercise is being taken out rather than more of it is introduced.
Physical exercise and art, both taken out. Why? Because they have to get the grades, neck up, and that's a pity,
and they pay a price. So obesity, in the school in Naperville or in the district, Naperville in Illinois, obesity levels went down from thirty percent to three percent among the
students that hell have repercussions not just for the students lives there that they're more comfortable that they're happier it has repercussions
and consequences for the rest of their lives they're much less susceptible and
prone to the chronic illnesses such as cancer heart failure it's a win-win on
so many levels, much less susceptible to diabetics. So that's obesity. What they also find at Naperville
is that the grades went up significantly. In fact, usually the U.S. doesn't do very well, doesn't do very well when it comes to those international tests,
math and science tests that they do. I think it's usually in eighth grade. Well, Naperville is an exception. They scored number six in the world in mathematics and number one in the world
in science. Now, people argue, well, Naperville is an affluent neighborhood or district, and
it's true. How about other places? Well, they introduced exercise in very poor areas, in
inner cities. For example, in Titusville, Pennsylvania, where many people are way below, the average
is way below the average income for the state. Before they introduced exercise, school performance,
they were significantly below state average, Pennsylvania's average.
After introducing exercise within a year,
they went up to 17% above state average,
with the only change being that year, introducing physical exercise.
They've seen this in other schools, in other districts as well.
And what they also saw in the same school, in Titusville, that fistfights, for example, they noticed violence disappeared completely as a result of the exercise.
What they found also in a school in Iowa, where they introduced physical exercise,
disciplinary problems went down from 225 to 95 in one year in another school in
Kansas also inner city disciplinary problems went down by 67% after the
introduced exercise we're much less likely to be voluntary it calms us it
us to our natural state of being which is much calmer as opposed to being angry and upset and
people need to let out that steam and unfortunately very often that steam is let out in fights with
aggression and this is a much healthier way to divert that healthy energy let me show you a
clip from one of my favorite movies, Legally Blonde. And it's the part where a woman is
just being charged with the murder of her husband. And our very own law school graduate,
Reese Witherspoon defends her. Whoops, let me get to it. Thank you.
Videos, legally, here it is.
We're defending Brooke Windham, whose very wealthy husband was found shot to death in their Beacon Hill mansion.
Gold digger?
You'd think so, since the stiff was 60, but she was rich on her own, some kind of fitness empire. You can buy her exercise tapes on infomercials. Wait, are you talking about Brooke Taylor?
Maiden named Taylor.
You know her? She's at Delta Neal.
She wasn't in my pledge class. She graduated four years before me. But I used to take her class at the Los Angeles Sports Club. She's amazing.
Amazing? Oh.
She can make you lose like three pounds in one class. She's completely gifted.
Well, in all likelihood, she's completely guilty as well.
I just don't think Brooke could have done this.
Exorcist gives you endorphins. Endorphins make you happy.
Happy people just don't shoot their husbands. They just don't.
There you go. Sorry.
You know, in the book, I talk about the happiness revolution.
And I think, based on a lot of research, that the foundation for a happiness revolution has to come with an exercise revolution.
Why? Because if we don't exercise, we're fighting against nature. So the foundation, the basis of the happiness revolution has to start neck down through the body.
Let me move on to a second mind-body intervention,
and that is meditation.
So what is meditation? I was first introduced to it through yoga.
I got injured playing squash.
My back, they told me yoga would help. I started yoga, it helped my back, and I got so much more out of it, in fact so much more out of it,
that I'm doing my teacher training now with Debbie Cohen and will become a yoga instructor hopefully very soon if she passes me.
There are other forms of mindfulness meditation, sitting meditation.
There is Tai Chi, Qigong.
There is meditation that just focuses on the breath. There is meditation that focuses on compassion. There are a few common elements to most types of meditation. Let me mention a few of them.
First of all, it's focusing on one thing. Whether it's the movement, whether it's the posture, whether it's the breath,
whether it's compassion and loving kindness, whether it's a flame, whatever it is. But it's focusing, whether it's a prayer, it's focusing on one thing.
Usually, most forms of meditation, the foundation is deep breathing. In a sense, the way a baby breathes, belly breathing.
Breathing all the way into your belly and then slowly, gently, gracefully breathing out.
Deep breathing is usually the foundation, whether it's of Tai Chi, yoga or sitting meditation.
And finally, there is no good or bad meditation. Meditation, in a sense, doesn't have a purpose when you're meditating.
You're giving yourself the permission to be human. There is no, oh, I just had an amazing meditation, oh, or I just feel enlightened.
In fact, let me tell you a story about how I became enlightened through meditation.
So, last year, I used to travel quite a bit. We lived in Israel, but I traveled once a month on average to the U.S. for a few days.
And when I traveled here, I used to give talks, but I also used that time as a form of retreat.
And what I would do is I would practice a lot of yoga, much more than I did in Israel.
I did a lot of meditation. I had a lot of time between talks.
So I had plenty of time, and I used it as a retreat. And I remember one time coming home, back to Israel.
And just to give you the context, in Israel, we live in a city just outside Tel Aviv called Ramat Gan.
and we live, our house is in a 20-story building. We live on the 10th floor, and the view is just breathtaking.
Now, Israel is a very tiny country, so I can see both sides of Israel, the Mediterranean on one side. I can see the mountains of Samaria on the other side.
Just a gorgeous view. And one of the things that I like to do is every morning, because I'm a morning person, I wake up usually before the rest of the family,
I sit down in the dining room and look outside through the glass window. We have a glass window.
Since it's so high, it's fortified glass, of course, and part of it does not open. But I look through that part that does not open outside.
And I do it very often.
And I remember coming back from this particular trip from the U.S. and looking outside, and suddenly all the colors seemed so much brighter.
The world seemed so much clearer.
And I said to myself, wow, I must have become enlightened.
Because I've read in books and I've heard people talking about it that when you become enlightened, everything becomes clear. The world becomes even more beautiful than it already is.
And I was sitting there on the sofa and just admiring the strong colors, the beauty, the clarity of everything.
And I said to myself, after so many years, I've been meditating for over 10 years.
After so many years, I'm finally enlightened.
And I started to act differently because, you know, enlightened people don't go around telling people that they're enlightened.
Well, this is an exception.
So I didn't even tell Tommy that I'm enlightened. But I was walking on air.
And the next day, the next morning, I would wake up and again my ritual observation of the mountains in the distance.
And I said, wow, the world is so beautiful.
I'm enlightened and that went on for a few days and then one day Tommy and I were sitting together in the lounge and
just chatting
and you know she was looking outside and I was looking outside and she said
you know finally when you went away you know after so long I finally was able to clean the window I said
I said what
and she said And, you know, I haven't been able to get out there, but I got this machine, you know, the two-sided machine with a magnet. I was finally able to get it, and I finally cleaned the window.
So much for my enlightenment.
So, you know, maybe there is enlightenment. I don't know.
But the key with meditation is not about reaching that stage when everything suddenly becomes so clear. You know, I think a quicker path would be to clean the window.
But that's not what meditation is about. Meditation is about being present, being in the here and now, struggling with being in the here and now. And when we lose our thoughts, when we lose our focus on the breath, simply bringing it back. That is the practice, losing it and bringing it back, losing it and bringing it back. And that's how we exercise our mind to be more focused, to be more mindful.
So let me share with you some of the studies on meditation.
And once you start meditation or yoga, and by the way, you will find what is right for you.
Being ADHD, it was very difficult for me to do sitting meditation.
Much more conducive for me to do yoga.
Because I'm working hard, it keeps my mind focused on the posture.
For other people, the right thing is sitting meditation, just breathing.
For others, it's thinking about certain things. For many people, it's praying.
Whatever works for you. And it can be, of course, a few things. You can pray and do yoga.
So let me share with you some of the studies. The real serious studies on meditation started by looking at the tip of the stem, at the meditators, people who have been doing it for many years, for a very long time.
And what they asked the researchers like Richie Davidson, University of Wisconsin,
in John Kabat-Zinn from University of Amherst, Worcester, people like Herbert Benson, Paul
Ekman from one of the UCs, and other people, when they wanted to study meditation, you suggest some people who have been meditating for a very long time, serious meditators, and we
want to study their brain.
So they did, and they brought them in, and what they looked for, the first thing, remember, left to right prefrontal cortex ratio. And if you remember, we talked about it,
people who are happier generally have more activation on the left side of the prefrontal cortex. People who are less happy have more activation on the right side of the prefrontal cortex.
So that ratio is important,
and it's one of the, quote-unquote, objective means of measuring happiness.
One of the things that they have found is that there is very high correlation between what our brain looks like under the scanner and our self-report about how happy we are.
Not 100% correlation, not a one, but pretty high,
suggesting that self-report are quite reliable. But anyway, so they wanted to look at the brain of the meditators. And when they looked at the general public,
we all exist on a bell curve. the happier people are further on
more activation on the left side the less happy people are further more activation higher ratio on the right side
and then they brought in the meditators
and they measured their left to right prefrontal cortex
and here is what they found
this is the normal bell curve this is where the meditators were this is from 2001 since they have found numerous meditators that are quite literally off the chart
suggesting very high levels of well-being and happiness being susceptible to positive emotions and resilient in the face of painful emotions.
So this is a remarkable result again results that they had not seen before until they measured these meditators. The other things that they were interested in looking at
the other important indicator for well-being and calmness is the startle response.
and when you hear a bang, you startle
and the startle response is important because the easier you get startled
generally it's correlated with higher levels of anxiety susceptibility at least to anxiety
and everyone has the startle response to some degree even marksmen and women in the military
who shoot their guns every day and they try and remain completely focused
even they startle when the gun goes off they flinch very slightly but they do so it's impossible to suppress the startle response
or so they thought when paul eckman brought these meditators in and asked them to maintain
complete equanimity and calmness and he startled them there was no reaction whatsoever
first time in recorded history that people are have been able to suppress the startle response Here is what Daniel Goleman writes about this in his book, Destructive Emotions.
Given that the larger someone's startle, the more intensely that person tends to experience upsetting emotions.
Osser's performance had tantalizing implications, suggesting a remarkable level of emotional equanimity.
That equanimity was also contagious, so people who tried to argue with these monks very often had a hard time becoming angry or upset,
even if the topic was upset personally upsetting to them such as scientists arguing about the
existence of god and they said i couldn't get upset because calm is contagious just like
happiness is now some of you may not be 100 clear about what the startle response is so for those Those of you who are not, I've prepared a very brief clip.
Alright, now you understand.
When they studied these meditators, essentially what they were doing was applying what we've talked about, the growing tip statistic.
What Maslow talks about is the growing tip statistic.
Studying the best, because if you want to advance knowledge, if you want to be able to better apply ideas that work, you don't study the average teacher, you study Marva Collins.
You don't study the average meditator who thinks he's enlightened. You study the meditators who have been doing it for many years.
The idea is that the process is within the reach of anyone who applies himself or herself with enough determination.
In other words, this is not just for the select few who can meditate for 30 years, 8 hours a day.
It can be applied because the process is relatively simple.
to all of us daniel goleman from the perspective of neuroscience the point of all this research has
nothing to do with demonstrating that oscar or any other extraordinary person may be remarkable
in him or herself but rather to stretch the field's assumptions about human possibility
about our potential some of these key assumptions have already begun to expand in part due to a a revolution in neuroscience's supposition about the malleability of the brain itself
remember neuroplasticity neurogenesis these concepts that i and people how scientists like
richie davidson identified that our brain is malleable it can change and one of the ways
to change it is through meditation now this is all well and good so we can apply this process with determination to our lives. But how many people here seriously would say,
okay, that sounds great, I want my left side of the prefrontal cortex to be more active, so I'm going to go off to the Himalayas
and meditate for 30 years, 8 hours a day. I mean, how many people are really prepared to do this? How many people have time for 2 hours a day of meditation?
The second problem with this research is that it's correlational.
there's no causation here maybe Lama Oster was born that way and that's why he was attracted to meditation
maybe Matthias Ricard has written a book on happiness he was born that way with a remarkable left to right prefrontal cortex his by the way was literally off the charts
but the main problem still remains beyond causation is the time do we have the time do we have the patience
to meditate so often and so much
Now, when I found out, when I started to meditate, to do yoga, I really saw the benefits of it. And I said, okay, so I'm getting benefits when I'm doing it for half an hour a day.
What if I do a real long retreat? And they have some great 10-day long retreats.
And I said to Tommy, you know, I want to go to a 10-day retreat. And Tommy knows me pretty well. And she said, you know, why don't you try, you know, it's not all or nothing.
Why don't you try a one-day retreat first before you go on the 10-day retreat? And I said, you know, that's a good idea.
And I went to a one-day retreat, which is not very far from here in Cambridge.
And I went to this retreat, and I was very excited. It was on a Saturday, and I was looking forward to it all week. And I said, I'm starting the process of enlightenment, of course, through this one-day retreat.
And right after that one-day retreat, once I proved to Tommy that it's good for me, and she'll see how calm I am after, she'll say, sure, we'll go for the 10-day retreat.
So I went to that one-day retreat, and the one-day retreat, we came in, and there was a gentleman who was sitting in front of the class with a beard,
looking very calm, and I said, I'm going to look like him at the end of the day,
minus the beard, and we sat down, and he said, we're going to start with sitting meditation.
So we all sat, you know, we had our cushions. i need a few cushions you know there we were sitting there i put my hands here and he said
okay now breathe deeply through your nostrils and then breathe out again and we did that and i was
sitting there in my mind you know being adhd started to wonder but he said if the mind wanderers bring it back to the focus and we were sitting there and um for what seemed like a very long
time. And I stayed there and I said, okay, your mind wanders, it's okay, come back to it. And I
continued to sit there and we sat for 45 minutes. And at the end he said, okay, you know, gently,
slowly open your eyes and stand up. And he said, what we're going to do now, the second part,
after the 45 minute first part of sitting meditation, we're going to do some walking
meditation and he illustrated and then we walked behind him around in a circle and we walked very
slowly very diligently just focusing on each step lifting up the leg and he said just focus on the
movement be present in the here and now and if you mind wanders which mine did constantly bring it back to the walking and continue to breathe deeply just like you did during the sitting
meditation so we were walking around the room for a very long time and we walked and we continued to
walk around that room and my mind continued to wander and I got bored so what I did was I
started to look around at the other people and they were all walking in the circle and then I
looked to where the teacher was sitting and next to the teacher there was a piece of paper i thought
oh interesting i wonder what it says there so i continued to walk and then i got to the piece
of paper again and i said oh it's a schedule how interesting and i didn't have enough time to actually read what it said there so i said next time around i have something to look forward to
so I continued to walk and I see oh I see this is what we did 45 minutes of sitting meditation and after that 45 minutes of walking meditation huh I
wonder what's next and I continued to walk and now I had something to look forward I was excited and I looked just below in 45 minutes of sitting
meditation and then 45 minutes of walking meditation whoa and another set
of sitting and walking oh and then lunch I wonder what we do after lunch 45 minutes of sitting meditation and walking whoa and after that walking
meditation so I thought to myself wow this is incredible I'll see you next
time gee and I walked out I just I couldn't take it so and and and I ran
home but I must I was a little bit embarrassed so I thought wait maybe I'll spend the day outside you know and just come back home and seem enlightened at
least but I didn't so I called Tommy and I told her you know do you want to have
breakfast together and we did she gives me the permission to be human I don't
see myself going on a 10-day retreat I don't see myself going on a 30-year
retreat. And my question was then, as it is now, how can meditation help people who don't
want to or simply can't meditate for such a long time? And don't get me wrong, I do recommend these retreats. There are people who go to these retreats and come out looking
differently. I mean, I know many of my friends have been there. But that's, again, a one-day retreat or a 10-day retreat. Some people have gone to as long as three-month retreat, and
they are good, just not for me. So what can we do? John Kabat-Zinn in his research showed
how meditation can apply to the people who don't want to do full days, who just have
45 minutes a day or as little as 15 minutes a day for meditation or yoga or some form
of mindfulness. And he did two things. First of all, he showed how it helps for people who
do less than the 30 years. And second, equally important, he showed causation. So he took
two groups in one of his studies, two groups. The one group, both groups wanted to do meditation, so they expressed an interest. One group he put on a waiting list, and he said, you'll
participate in the seminar in about three months. It was four months. In four months, still participate in the seminar, were all booked out.
The second group started the meditation regime workshop then.
And the regime was essentially 45 minutes of meditation a day.
During the weekend they were together where they learned some techniques, but during the week when they were at home, 45 minutes a day of meditation.
And then he compared them to the control group, the group that was waiting for a retreat, waiting for the lessons, because he wanted them to be of the same kind, people who want to do meditation.
One that actually started, one that he's going to start soon.
And then he measured anxiety, and compared to the control group, anxiety levels of those who did meditation for eight weeks,
just eight weeks, 45 minutes a day on average.
Anxiety decreased significantly.
Then he looked at their happiness level, at the positive, not just the negative to the zero, the zero to the positive. And they were happier.
They had better moods after as little as eight weeks. But here are the clinchers. He then said, well, it's not enough to just self-report. It could be placebo, which is great,
but he wanted to see if there was something else beyond just the placebo.
And here is what he found. He looked at the left to right prefrontal cortex.
And after as little as eight weeks, there was a significant difference in those individuals who meditated. Now, this is a remarkable result.
Remember, until 1998, scientists were sure that the brain is not malleable, does not change past the age of three or so.
And suddenly here, within as little as eight weeks, these meditators or individuals, you know, regular people doing 45 minutes of meditation a day,
are changing the way their brain functions, making them more susceptible to positive emotions, more resilient in the face of painful emotions.
Herbert Benson from our medical school here has shown that with as little as 15 to 20 minutes a day of meditation,
you see a significant change over time in levels of well-being,
emotional well-being as well as physical well-being. Because the other study that John Kabat-Zinn did with these meditators
was inject both groups, the control group who were waiting and the meditators, he injected them with cold bacteria.
And what he wanted to do, what he wanted to measure was how would their body react in terms of antibodies.
And what he found was that the meditators' immune response was significantly stronger than those who didn't meditate,
who were waiting to meditate, just based on eight weeks of meditation, 45 minutes a day.
And we know that when we're calmer, we're less susceptible to illnesses. When we're stressed, we're more susceptible to illnesses.
So meditation strengthens both the psychological immune system in making us more resilient, as well as the physical immune system.
Mindfulness has been used in numerous areas, numerous places as therapy.
more and more so today both as in together with cognitive behavioral therapy together with
medicine medication as well as on its own and it's been shown to be extremely effective the book i recommend if you want to get a good outline of what the field has to say is called the mindful
way through depression that talks about how mindfulness can help us overcome major depression mild depression, as well as things like anxiety
and how it can also help other psychological disorders.
And one of the things, for example, that they show there, we know from, unfortunately, we know that once someone has major depression, the likelihood of it reappearing, whether it's a month later
or sometimes years later, is much higher than if we've never had major depression. Why? Think about what we have discussed before.
What we talked about is how the brain creates neural pathways. Now, if a neural pathway has been created and it's a strong neural pathway of depression,
very often something which is relatively mild that happens can send us back to that neural pathway. So we go through a relatively hard period, nothing that serious,
But immediately, the brain looks for the largest neural pathway, the largest river, metaphorically speaking, and it goes there.
And we have the major depression again, with little reason. And after we have it two or three times, the neural pathways are even stronger, even more likely to recur.
what they have found when they introduced mindfulness meditation or mindfulness therapy
in addition to cognitive behavioral therapy was that it reduced the likelihood of recurrence of major depression among people who have major depression or had major depression
reduces the likelihood by over 50% of relapse.
That's in a longitudinal study.
So this really helps. It also helps deal with non-major depression. It helps dealing with sadness.
Now, how does it work? How does it work?
Let me, again, very briefly, I do recommend this book. We could have a whole course on this book. The book has also got an eight-week program, which is fantastic.
Its first level, it's about awareness and acceptance of the body signal. What do they mean here? You see, whenever we enter experience and emotion,
there is always a physical manifestation. to it. Positive emotions such as happiness, it could be butterflies or just feeling very
broad in the upper body or whatever it is, but also painful emotions. For example, if
I experience, personally when I experience anxiety, it's here. I feel it here. Or here in the knot in my stomach that I talked about. People who experience depression or
even sadness feel it somewhere. Again, whether it's in the stomach, whether it's in the shoulders there's always a physical manifestation to an emotional experience and what they are saying
and what the research has shown is that when we begin to experience a painful emotion
immediately going and becoming mindful aware of whatever the physical manifestation is
so instead of beginning to ruminate and to dwell on why am i depressed what's going on
what's happening not again i hope this won't start instead of going into this rumination
going immediately to the physical manifestation of it to the body so come i'm beginning to
feel stress okay and focusing on it and accepting that not not trying to fix it as we'll talk about
in a minute simply accepting it for what it is looking at it and say oh that's interesting
oh it's it's quite a big knot oh no it's small oh it's getting actually bigger as opposed to saying
i want it to go away oh it is going away that's interesting but that's not the purpose the purpose
is simply to become aware of it simply to become aware of whatever the physical manifestation
of the emotion is now why does this work it works because it creates an alternative neural pathway
with the usual neural pathway that is created when we feel dis-ease
is going into the mind, ruminating about it and usually going to the channel that existed before the channels or channels that existed before
and these are channels associated with our depression or our previous negative experiences
that have been reinforced what we're doing now, instead of going into these reinforced channels inside our mind and further reinforcing them we're creating an alternative one.
Oh, pain? Let's go to the body.
And that alternative channel, the reason why it works, is because that's when we're drawing, that's when we're going to the body's natural ability to heal.
Most of the illnesses that we face, the body has the capacity, most, not all, has the capacity to heal itself. Most of the cuts that you get, you don't need to do anything about it. In fact, you shouldn't do anything about small cuts.
You know, play with it, look at it, touch it. Just let nature take its course. It will fix it by itself.
Same with digestion. You don't need to think about digestion. The body has its own internal wisdom, its own internal healer.
And this is exactly what happens when you go and you divert attention from,
oh, what am I going to do about it? What's happening? It's so terrible. I hope I won't feel this way. I hope I feel better soon. And why am I feeling this way? What's the cause?
Sometimes it's important to do it and to analyze and to write about it as opposed to ruminate about it or to talk to someone about it as opposed to ruminating about it.
But the most effective in most situations is to just go to the bodily sensation and be aware of it.
Accept it. Don't try and fix it. Just let it be there and just observe it.
And our internal healer will take care of itself.
the key in order to become adapt at it is to practice it's to practice that to do it over and over again just like everything else that we've discussed in
this class there are no quick fixes how do we practice it first and this is part of their eight-week program which I'm doing right now the first is body scan
become aware of your body just by lying down and thinking and observing first of your foot, then becoming aware of your knee, becoming aware of sensations in your quads,
becoming aware of sensations in your stomach, wherever it is, going through the whole body,
and practicing and becoming more aware.
And this is doing it in a cold state.
This is doing it in practice, in a simulator. And then when we're in a hot state, when we actually experience that emotion, that painful emotion, we're ready to go to it, and we know what to do.
Practice also means when we lose focus, we go back to it. And that's the practice.
The practice is not remaining completely centered for 30 minutes.
The practice is losing and coming back, losing focus and coming back again.
And then also practicing in real life.
So whenever I feel stressed, immediately going, okay, so what's the physical manifestation of it?
Now here we're talking about the emotion, we're talking about the body.
You can also practice by using cognitive reconstruction.
How?
For instance, let's say I'm thinking about a talk that I have to give tonight.
And I'm very nervous for it. Large audience, important audience. And every time I think of it, my initial inclination is stress.
And I get the adrenaline feel here, and I don't feel good about it.
Or the knot in my stomach.
So how do I deal with it? Each time I think about it, I say, okay, where am I feeling it in the body?
Another way of dealing with it is cognitively reconstructing it and saying instead of stress, what a privilege.
Remember I told you I had a very large client that I had to speak to and was very stressed about that talk. And every time my mind went to stress, within half a second,
I said, no, it's a privilege.
It's so wonderful that I have the opportunity to do it.
Again, this is different from avoiding. This is different from repressing.
There is a time to simply accept and to give ourselves the permission to be human.
However, it's useless to just constantly ruminate about it and simply strengthen the neural pathways.
So this reaction of either going to the physical body or sometimes going to the cognitive reconstruction can be very useful.
Remember, when we want change, we want to draw as much as possible on A, B, and C, on affect, on behavior, and cognition.
And these are just two very helpful techniques. Again, I use it constantly, whether it's going to the body or going and cognitively reconstructing.
Extremely helpful. And again, the data shows how helpful it is.
Let's try it.
Let's do a quick mindfulness meditation
and incorporating some of the ideas that I discuss now and things that we've discussed in the past.
So sit comfortably in your seats as much as possible,
your back straight, leaning on the back if that is more comfortable.
Elongate your neck as much as possible.
Create a straight line in your upper body.
Plant your feet as comfortably as you can.
on the floor. If they're across and you feel comfortable, uncross them. And rest your hands
either on your legs or folded, however you feel comfortable. And if you feel comfortable,
close your eyes. Wherever your attention is now, wherever your focus is now, bring it
to your breath. Breathe deeply into your belly and then breathe slowly, gently, gracefully
out. Take a deep breath in and slow, gentle, quiet exhalation. And repeat this a few times.
If your mind wanders, simply, gently bring it back to the breath and practice.
As you continue to breathe, shift your attention, your focus to your body, your feet, shins,
your legs, your waist, your belly, your back.
Just scan your whole body, your chest, neck, your head, and find one area in your body that is slightly tense, that you feel more than others, that is less relaxed than the rest of the body.
And whatever that part of the body is, shift your attention there and observe the discomfort.
Observe the tension.
Just observe and accept it is.
Continue to breathe deeply as you're observing that part of the body.
And just look how interesting it is that you have that sensation there.
with each breath embrace it there's nothing right there is nothing wrong with how you feel
the feeling simply is and continue with the breath to breathe into that part and then out
of that part, simply observing it, accepting it, being with it. Continue to be with that
part of your body, with your breath, and experience the experience, whatever it is, it is. And
then gently say goodbye to the focus on that particular part, very gently, because you
just embraced it and return to your breath and with your breath wash cleanse your entire body
starting with your souls going all the way up to the top of your head and each breath introduces
deeper calm, deeper acceptance, deeper being.
Just experience, just feel the lightness, the light that comes from acceptance,
from our natural state of being.
Take another deep breath in, slow, gentle, quiet exhalation.
And with the next exhalation, open your eyes.
If the person next to you is asleep, again, just gently nudge them or embrace them.
The effects of mindfulness meditation, mindfulness therapy, is quite literally mind-boggling.
what we're doing and what mindful therapy does is change our focus from doing to being how is that
you see usually usually when we experience something stressful or when our mind goes to a sad place
our immediate reaction is how can I fix it?
how can I fix it? and we try to fix it by thinking about alternatives or by getting ourselves to feel better by thinking through the problem that we're facing
why? because
this fixing mind works because of the fixing mind that we have science and technology and progress and it's because of the fixing mind
the thinking mind that you got in here you didn't get in here because you were a great meditator you got in here because you did well in your tests you
were able to solve problems well on the SATs and that's a good thing and that's
important skill but very often it's counterproductive when it comes to
dealing with mental psychological issues we gravitate toward it we want to
fix it but very often it's counterproductive just like it would be counterproductive to try and meddle
with the digestion that our body goes through the digestive process it happens independent of us
if we try and play with it open it look at it help it will only hurt it why because the internal
mind, the internal healer, the internal wisdom knows best to deal with certain things. Not
everything, but certain things, such as digestion, such as very often, not always, but very often with mental afflictions, with painful emotions. So we're moving, we're shifting our focus
from trying to fix to simply be with that emotion, with that experience, with a manifestation
of the pain in their book William who teaches at Oxford trying to get rid of
depression in the usual problem-solving way trying to fix what's wrong with us
just digs us in deeper rumination is part of the problem not part of the solution now the emphasis here is on rumination it's not and we've talked
about a lot it's not the fact that if you're writing your journal it's not helpful it's good for you to write about issues that you're dealing with in your
journal it's good to talk to a very close friend but just rumination going
over the same scenario over and over again ruminating about it trying to fix it very often makes it worse and would be better off just going to the emotion
going to the physical manifestation try it see what's right for you it may be right for you to, you know, write for half an hour on one occasion and then just meditate
on it for ten minutes. Or it may be right for you to only write about it. It's different for different people, but what I'm doing here is I'm adding another tool to your psychological
toolbox. And just like we can cognitively reconstruct, as opposed to seeing it as a
threat to see it as a challenge, as opposed to seeing it as a threat to see it as a privilege,
as opposed to seeing it as a failure or to see it as a learning opportunity,
we can also have emotional reconstruction
where instead of just thinking and ruminating about it, we go to the experience.
With a shift from trying to ignore or eliminate physical discomfort to paying attention with friendly curiosity,
we can transform, quietly, literally transform our experience. I'm going to leave you today with a last tip
and this is something that is very important and that I highly recommend doing for all of you, no exception
what I highly recommend doing is
breathing
it's very, very, very important to breathe
and in fact it's the one thing that's common to all the mindfulness meditation practices and something that you can introduce into your life of course I mean proper breathing
something you can introduce into your life, even if you don't meditate for 15 minutes or 45 minutes a day.
What I'm talking about here is deep breathing, because here is what happens. In our modern world, we're mostly stressed and anxious.
As a result of this, our breathing becomes shallow.
And as a result of shallow breathing, when our breathing is shallow, we become even more stressed and anxious, and we go into this vicious cycle, vicious downward spiral
of the fight-or-flight response.
And that's how we go through most of our days.
Fortunately, we can reverse this. And we can reverse this very quickly because what we also know is that calm and well-being leads to deep breathing, and deep breathing in turn leads to calm and well-being.
We can reverse the fight-or-flight response and enter what Herbert Benson calls the relaxation response within as little as three deep breaths.
We can introduce these three deep breaths strategically throughout the day, just before class starts, just when a class ends, just when I wake up in the morning,
or the last thing before I go to bed.
Three deep breaths, strategic points through the day, can transform a life.
Andrew Weil, graduate of our medical school, now the University of Arizona,
in his wonderful CD talks about breathing. If I had to limit my advice on healthier living to just one tip, it would be simply to learn how to breathe correctly.
And that means breathing like a baby breathes into the stomach. I told you I'm not going to teach you much new in this course. You know how to breathe. You learned how to breathe when you were born.
All we're doing now is chipping away the excess stone so that you go back to your natural wisdom, your natural healer.
In a wonderful book, Ali Crum's dad, she did the article with Ellen Langer,
Thomas Crum, gives some good advice about how we can reverse the flight or flight response. And one of the things that the advice that he said is that each time you get to a red light,
use it as an opportunity to breathe deeply, whether when you're walking and you get to a red light or in the car.
Now, in the past, I introduced it. In the past, every time I got to a red light, it was annoying,
especially if the light had just changed from green.
Now, whenever I get to a red light, it's an opportunity,
and I breathe deeply.
Introduce deep breathing into your life just a few times a day,
and that can have far-reaching consequences.
So, I'll see you next week, and until then, breathe.